You might be wondering why I'm wearing sunglasses,
قد تتسائلون لما ذا أرتدي نظارات شمسية
and one answer to that is, because I'm here to talk about glamour.
وأحد الأجوبة هو لأنني هنا لأتحدث عن الإبهار
So, we all think we know what glamour is. Here it is.
إذاً، نحن جميعاً نعتقد أننا نعرف ماذا يعني الانبهار
It's glamorous movie stars, like Marlene Dietrich.
إنها نجمة سينما مبهرة، مثل مارلين ديتريتش
And it comes in a male form, too --
وهذا يتضمن الذكور أيضاً
very glamorous.
غاية في الابهار والشهرة
Not only can he shoot, drive, drink -- you know, he drinks wine,
لا يمكنة فقط أن يطلق النار ويقود، إنه يشرب الكحول أيضاً
there actually is a little wine in there --
هناك فعلياً بعضاً من الخمر هناك
and of course, always wears a tuxedo.
وبالطبع دائماً يرتدي ملابس السهرة
But I think that glamour actually has a much broader meaning --
لكنني أعتقد أن الانبهار حقيقة له معنى أوسع بكثير
one that is true for the movie stars and the fictional characters,
طبعاً إن نجوم السينما والرموز الخيالية هي أحد أنواعه
but also comes in other forms.
لكنه أيضاً يأتي بصور متعددة
A magazine?
مجلة.؟
Well, it's certainly not this one.
حسناً، بالتأكيد ليست هذه
This is the least glamorous magazine on the newsstand -- it's all about sex tips.
هذه المجلة هي الأقل إبهارا في حامل المجلات وهي عن نصائح جنسية
Sex tips are not glamorous.
النصائح الجنسية ليست مبهرة
And Drew Barrymore, for all her wonderful charm,
و درو باريمور مع كل جمالها الساحر
is not glamorous either.
ليست مبهرة أيضاً
But there is a glamour of industry.
لكن هناك صناعة للإبهار
This is Margaret Bourke-White's --
هذه مارغاريت بورك
one of her pictures she did.
إحدى صورها
Fantastic, glamorous pictures
رائعة، صورة مبهرة
of steel mills and paper mills and all kinds of glamorous industrial places.
عن الطواحين المعدنية والطواحين الورقية وكافة الأماكن الصناعية المبهرة
And there's the mythic glamour
هذا هو الابهار الأسطوري
of the garage entrepreneur.
لرواد العمل في المرآب
This is the Hewlett-Packard garage.
هذا هو مرآب هيوليت باكارد
We know everyone who starts a business in a garage
ونحن نعلم أن أي شخص يبدأ العمل في مرآب
ends up founding Hewlett-Packard.
سينتهي المطاف به عند هيوليت باكارد
There's the glamour of physics.
هذا الإبهار الفيزيائي
What could be more glamorous than understanding the entire universe,
ما الذي يمكن أن يكون أكثر إبهارا من فهم الكون
grand unification? And, by the way, it helps if you're Brian Greene --
توحيد شامل و، بالمناسبة، سيكون أمراً مساعداً لو كنا برايان غرين
he has other kinds of glamour.
لديه أنواع أخرى من الإبهار
And there is, of course, this glamour.
ويوجد بالطبع هذا الإبهار
This is very, very glamorous: the glamour of outer space --
هذا شديد الإبهار إنه إبهار الفضاء الخارجي
and not the alien-style glamour,
وليس الإنبهار بالمخلوقات الفضائية
but the nice, clean, early '60s version.
وإنما إصدار الستينات الجميل والنقي
So what do we mean by glamour?
إذا مالذي نعنيه الإبهار
Well, one thing you can do if you want to know what glamour means
حسناً، هناك شيء يمكن فعله إذا أردت معرفة ماذا يعني الإبهار
is you can look in the dictionary.
وهو أن تنظر في المعجم
And it actually helps a lot more if you look in a very old dictionary,
وبالحقيقة سيكون من المفيد أكثر إذا بحثت في معجم قديم جداً
in this case the 1913 dictionary.
في هذه الحالة نفضل معجم عام 1913
Because for centuries, glamour had a very particular meaning,
لأنه ولمدة عقود، كلمة الإبهار كان لها معنى محدد جداً
and the word was actually used differently from the way we think of it.
والكلمة تم استخدامها بشكل مختلف عن ما نعتقد أنها فعلياً الآن
You had "a" glamour.
انت مبهر
It wasn't glamour as a quality -- you "cast a glamour."
الإبهار هو ليس كنوع من الجودة -- أنت تشع الانبهار
Glamour was a literal magic spell.
الإبهار كانت تعويذة سحرية حرفية
Not a metaphorical one, the way we use it today,
وليست مجازية كما نستخدمها اليوم
but a literal magic spell associated with witches and gypsies
لقد كانت تعويذة سحرية حرفية مرتبطة بالسحرة والغجر
and to some extent, Celtic magic.
وإلى حد ما ، سحر السيلتيك
And over the years, around the turn of the 20th century,
وبمرور السنين عند دخول القرن العشرين
it started to take on this other kind of deception --
بدأت تأخذ هذه الكلمة منحى مختلف من التضليل
this definition for any artificial interest in, or association with,
هذا التعريف لأي اهتمام مصطنع أو مرتبط
an object through which it appears delusively magnified or glorified.
بشيء أو بجسم عبر كونه ظاهراً بشكل وهمي أنه مضخم أو ممجد
But still, glamour is an illusion.
ولكن يبقى الانبهار مجرد وهم
Glamour is a magic spell.
الانبهار هو تعويذة سحر
And there's something dangerous about glamour
وهناك شيء خطير بالنسبة له
throughout most of history. When the witches cast a magic spell
خلال العصور، عندما تلقي الساحرات تعويذة سحرية
on you, it was not in your self-interest --
عليك لم يكن ذلك في نطاق اهتماماتك
it was to get you to act against your interest.
ولكن كان ذلك لكي تجعلك تتصرف عكس اهتماماتك
Well of course, in the 20th century,
حسناً بالطبع في القرن العشرين
glamour came to have this different meaning associated with Hollywood.
الانبهار جاء ليأخذ معنى آخر مرتبط بهوليوود
And this is Hedy Lamarr.
وهذه هي هيدي لامار
Hedy Lamarr said, "Anyone can look glamorous,
هيدي لامار قالت: "أي شخص يمكنه يبدو باهرا
all you have to do is sit there and look stupid." (Laughter)
كل ما عليكم فعله هو الجلوس هناك والتظاهر بالغباء."
But in fact, with all due respect to Hedy --
لكن في الحقيقة، مع كل الاحترام لهيدي
about whom we'll hear more later -- there's a lot more to it.
والتي سنتحدث عنها بالمزيد لاحقاً - يجب فعل الكثير لكي تبهر
There was a tremendous amount of technical achievement
لقد كان هناك مقداراً هائلاً من الإنجاز التقني
associated with creating this Hollywood glamour.
المرتبط بخلق هذا الانبهار في هوليوود
There were scores of retouchers and lighting experts and make-up experts.
كان هناك العشرات من الفنيين وخبراء الإضاءة وخبراء التجميل
You can go to the museum of Hollywood history in Hollywood
يمكنك الذهاب إلى متحف تاريخ هوليوود في هوليوود
and see Max Factor's special rooms that he painted different colors
وترى غرف ماكس فاكتور التي طلاها بألوان مختلفة
depending on the complexion of the star he was going to make up.
معتمداً على التعقيد في النجم الذي كان ينوي أن يكونه
So you've got this highly stylized portrait of something
والآن بعدما حصلتم على هذه اللوحة الفنية الفاخرة
that was not entirely of this earth -- it was a portrait of a star.
والتي لم تكون عن الأرض كلها -- كانت لوحة عن نجم
And actually, we see glamorized photos of stars all the time --
وبالحقيقة نحن نشاهد صوراً لنجوم تم تسليط الضوء عليهم طوال الوقت
they call them false color.
يدعونهم لون زائف
Glamour is a form of falsification,
الابهار هو نوع من التزييف
but falsification to achieve a particular purpose.
لكنه تزييف لتحقيق هدف معين
It may be to illuminate the star; it may be to sell a film.
من الممكن أن يكون لإنارة النجم، أو لبيع فيلم
And it involves a great deal of technique.
وهذا يتضمن كم هائل من التقنية
It's not -- glamour is not something --
لست أقول أن الابهار هو لاشيء
you don't wake up in the morning glamorous. I don't care who you are.
ولكنك لا تستيقظ في الصباح باهراً، لا يهمني من أنت
Even Nicole Kidman doesn't wake up in the morning glamorous.
حتى نيكول كيدمان لم تستيقظ فجأة ذات صباح بهذا الابهار
There is a process of "idealization, glorification and dramatization,"
هناك عملية معالجة مثالية، للتمجيد والدراماتيكية
and it's not just the case for people.
وهذا لا ينطبق فقط على الأشخاص
Glamour doesn't have to be people.
ليس من الضروري أن يكون الابهار للأشخاص فقط
Architectural photography --
التصوير المعماري
Julius Schulman, who has talked about transfiguration,
خوليوس سكالمان، الذي تكلم عن تغيير المظهر
took this fabulous, famous picture of the Kauffman House.
التقط هذه الصورة الرائعة والشهيرة لبيت كوفمان
Architectural photography is extremely glamorous.
التصوير المعماري هو مبهر للغاية
It puts you into this special, special world.
يضعك في عالم خاص جداً
This is Alex Ross's comic book art,
هذا هو كتاب أليكس روس عن الرسوم المتحركة
which appears to be extremely realistic,
الذي يظهر أنه واقعي جداً
as part of his style is he gives you a kind of realism in his comic art.
وكجزء من نموذجه يعطيك جزء من الواقعية في صوره المتحركة
Except that light doesn't work this way in the real world.
عدا أن الضوء لا يعمل بهذه الطريقة في الحياة الواقعية
When you stack people in rows,
وعندما تجمع الناس في صفوف
the ones in the background look smaller than the ones in the foreground --
الشخص في الخلف يظهر أصغر من الشخص في المقدمة
but not in the world of glamour.
لكن ليس في عالم الانبهار
What glamour is all about -- I took this from a blurb
إن كل ما يعنيه الانبهار -- لقد حصلت على هذا الإعلان المبالغ فيه
in the table of contents of New York magazine,
من لوحة المحتويات في مجلة نيو يورك
which was telling us that glamour is back --
والتي تقول لنا أن الابهار قد عاد --
glamour is all about transcending the everyday.
الابهار هو تجاوز الشيء المعتاد يومياً
And I think that that's starting to get at what the core
وأعتقد أن هذا بدأ يدخل في الجوهر
that combines all sorts of glamour is.
الذي يجمع كافة أنواع الابهار
This is Filippino Lippi's 1543 portrait of Saint Apollonia.
هذه اللوحة الفنية لفليبينو ليبي عن ساينت أبولونيا
And I don't know who she is either,
ولست أعرف من هي أيضاً
but this is the [16th] century equivalent of a supermodel.
ولكن هذه صورة مماثلة عن عارضة من القرن الخامس عشر
It's a very glamorous portrait.
إنها لوحة فنية مبهرة جداً
Why is it glamorous?
لماذا هي مبهرة
It's glamorous, first, because she is beautiful --
إنها مبهرة، أولاً، لأن الإمرأة جميلة
but that does not make you glamorous,
ولكن هذا لا يجعلك باهرا
that only makes you beautiful.
هذا فقط يجعلك جميلة
She is graceful, she is mysterious and she is transcendent,
إنها رشيقة، إنها غامضة، إنها متعالية
and those are the central qualities of glamour.
وهذه هي المركزيات في الابهار
You don't see her eyes; they're looking downward.
لست ترى أعينها، لأنها تنظر للأسف
She's not looking away from you exactly,
إنها لا تنظر بعيداً عنكم فعلياً
but you have to mentally imagine her world.
لكن يتوجب عليكم تخيل عالمها ذهنياً
She's encouraging you to contemplate this higher world
إنها تشجعكم لتتأملوا هذا العالم الراقي
to which she belongs, where she can be completely tranquil
الذي تنتمي إليه حيث يمكنها أن تكون هادئة تماماً
while holding the iron instruments of her death by torture.
ممسكة بالمعدات الحديدية التي عذبت بها حتى الموت
Mel Gibson's "Passion Of The Christ" -- not glamorous.
ميل غيبسون "آلام المسيح" -- ليس مبهرا
That's glamour:
هذا هو الابهار
that's Michelangelo's "Pieta," where Mary is the same age as Jesus
هذا مايكل أنجلوس بييتا حيث يكون عيسى بعمر مريم
and they're both awfully happy and pleasant.
وكلاهما سعيد جداً ومسرور
Glamour invites us to live in a different world.
الابهار يدعونا للعيش في عالم مختلف
It has to simultaneously be mysterious, a little bit distant --
علينا أن نكون غامضين وبعيدين بعض الشيء
that's why, often in these glamour shots,
وهذا ما تكون بسببه بعض اللقطات باهرة
the person is not looking at the audience,
الشخص لا ينظر إلى الجمهور
it's why sunglasses are glamorous --
لذلك فإن النظارات الشمسية باهرة
but also not so far above us that we can't identify with the person.
ولكنها ليست أعلى منا بكثير بحيث لا نستطيع تمميز الشخص
In some sense, there has to be something like us.
في مجال معين يجب أن يكون هناك شيء يشبهنا
So as I say, in religious art, you know, God is not glamorous.
لذلك كما قلت، في الفن الديني، تعلمون، الرب لايكون مبهرا
God cannot be glamorous because God is omnipotent,
الرب لا يمكن أن يكون مبهراً لأنه صاحب النفوذ الشامل والقهار
omniscient -- too far above us.
والعليم -- وكل هذه الأشياء هي أرقى منا بكثير
And yet you will see in religious art, saints or the Virgin Mary
ومع ذلك فإنك ترى في الفن الديني، القديسين أو مريم العذراء
will often be portrayed -- not always -- in glamorous forms.
يتم تصويرهم عادة -- ليس دائماً -- بهيئات مبهرة
As I said earlier, glamour does not have to be about people,
وكما قلت مسبقاً، فإن الابهار لا يشترط به أن يكون للناس
but it has to have this transcendent quality.
لكنه يجب أن يشمل هذه الجودة المتعالية
What is it about Superman?
والآن ماذا عن سوبرمان.؟
Aside from Alex Ross's style, which is very glamorous,
بغض النظر عن هيئة أليكس روس، والتي هي مبهرة جداً
one thing about Superman is he makes you believe that a man can fly.
أحد الأشياء في سوبرمان هي أنه يقنعك بأن الرجل يمكنه الطيران
Glamour is all about transcending this world
وكل مافي الابهار هو أنه يرتقي بالعالم
and getting to an idealized, perfect place.
ويذهب به إلى مكان مثالي
And this is one reason that modes of transportation
وهذا سبب كون وسائل النقل
tend to be extremely glamorous.
تميل إلى أن تكون شديدة الابهار
The less experience we have with them,
وكلما كانت خبرتنا بها أقل
the more glamorous they are.
كلما كانو أشد ابهارا
So you can do a glamorized picture of a car,
إذاً تستطيعون تكوين صورة سيارة تم شهرها
but you can't do a glamorized picture of traffic.
ولكن لا يمكنكم تكوين صورة عن ازدحام باهر
You can do a glamorized picture of an airplane, but not the inside.
يمكنكم تكوين صورة عن طائرة تم شهرها، ولكن لا يمكنكم القيام بذلك عما في داخلها
The notion is that it's going to transport you,
الفكرة أنها ستقوم بنقلك
and the story is not about, you know, the guy in front of you in the airplane,
والقصة ليست، كما تعلمون، حول الشخص في المقعد أمامكم في الطائرة
who has this nasty little kid, or the big cough.
مع ابنه الصغير المقرف أو السعال الشديد
The story is about where you're arriving,
القصة هي أين ستصلون
or thinking about where you're arriving.
أو التفكير في أين ستصلون
And this sense of being transported
وهذا الإحساس بكونك يتم نقلك
is one reason that we have glamour styling.
هو أحد أسباب امتلاكنا طراز مبهر
This sort of streamlining styling is not just glamorous
هذا النوع من التصميم المبسط ليس باهرا
because we associate it with movies of that period, but because,
لأننا نربطه بأفلام هذه الفترة، ولكن بسبب
in it's streamlining, it transports us from the everyday.
كونه تبسيط، إنه ينقلنا من الروتين اليومي
The same thing -- arches are very glamorous.
نفس الشيء-- القناطر إنها شديدة الابهار
Arches with stained glass -- even more glamorous.
القناطر ذات الزجاج المبقع -- هي أكثر ابهارا
Staircases that curve away from you are glamorous.
الإدراج التي تنحني بعيداً عنك تكون مبهرة
I happen to find that particular staircase picture very glamorous
صدف أني رأيت هذا الدرج بالتحديد شديد الابهار
because, to me, it captures the whole promise
لأنه وبالنسبة لي إنه يصور الوعد
of the academic contemplative life --
الذي تقدمة الحياة الأكاديمية التاملية
but maybe that's because I went to Princeton.
لكن ربما لأنني ذهبت إلى برينستون
Anyway, skylines are super glamorous,
على كل الأحوال، ناطحات السحاب خارقة الروعة
city streets -- not so glamorous.
شوارع المدن ليست بهذه الروعة
You know, when you get, actually to this town it has reality.
تعلمون عندما تصلون فعلياً إلى هذه البلدة فهي ذات واقعية
The horizon, the open road, is very, very glamorous.
الأفق، الطريق المفتوح، إنه شديد الروعة
There are few things more glamorous than the horizon --
هناك بعض الأشياء تكون أكثر روعة من الأفق
except, possibly, multiple horizons.
عدا الآفاق المتعددة و
Of course, here you don't feel the cold, or the heat --
بالتأكيد، هنا لاتشعرون بالبرودة، أو الحرارة
you just see the possibilities.
إنكم فقط ترون الاحتمالات
In order to pull glamour off, you need this Renaissance quality
ولكي تسحبو هذه الروعة فإنكم تحتاجون لانتفاضة ذات جودة
of sprezzatura, which is a term coined by Castiglione
كتلك "سبريزاتورا"، وهو مصطلح ابتدعه كاستيجيليون
in his book, "The Book Of The Courtier."
في كتابه "كتاب الأتباع"
There's the not-glamorous version of what it looks like today,
هذه هي النسخة الغير مبهرة من ما هو باهر فعلياً هذه الأيام
after a few centuries.
بعد عدة قرون
And sprezzatura is the art that conceals art.
سبريزاتورا هي الفن الذي يحجب الفن
It makes things look effortless.
إنها تجعل الأشايء تبدو بدون صعوبة
You don't think about how Nicole Kidman is maneuvering that dress --
أنتم لا تتسائلون كيف أن نيكول كيدمان ناورت هذا الرداء
she just looks completely natural.
إنها تبدو طبيعية كلياً
And I remember reading, after the Lara Croft movies,
وأنا أتذكر أني قرأت ، بعد أفلام لارا كرافت
how Angelina Jolie would go home completely black and blue.
كيف أن أنجلينيا جولي كلنت لتذهب للمنزل مغطاة بندب زرقاء وسوداء
Of course, they covered that with make-up,
لكنهم بالطبع أخفوا ذلك عن طريق المكياج
because Lara Croft did all those same stunts --
لأن لارا كرافت قامت بكل هذه الحيل المماثلة
but she doesn't get black and blue, because she has sprezzatura.
ولكنها لتم تصبح زرقاء وسوداء لأنها امتلكت السبريزاتورا
"To conceal all art and make whatever is done or said appear to be without effort":
لكي تخفي كل الفن وتصنع أي شيء، أو لنقول، تبدو وكأنه بدون مجهود
And this is one of the critical aspects of glamour.
وهذا أحد الجوانب الحساسة في الروعة
Glamour is about editing.
الابهار هو التعديل
How do you create the sense of transcendence,
كيف تقومون بصناعة هذا الحس من السمو
the sense of evoking a perfect world?
حس استحضار عالم مثالي
The sense of, you know, life could be better, I could join this --
حس، كما تعلمون، أن الحياة ممكن أن تكون أفضل، يمكنني الإنضمام إلى--
I could be a perfect person, I could join this perfect world.
يمكنني أن أكون شخص مثالي، ويمكنني الإنضمام إلى هذا العالم المثالي
We don't tell you all the grubby details.
نحن لا نخبركم عن كل التفاصيل القذرة
Now, this was kindly lent to me by Jeff Bezos, from last year.
لقد أقرضني هذا جيف بيزوس بكل لطف من العام الماضي
This is underneath Jeff's desk.
هذا أسفل مكتب جيف
This is what the real world of computers,
هذا ما يبدو عليه عالم من الكمبيوترات
lamps, electrical appliances of all kinds, looks like.
والمصابيح والمعدات الالكترونية من كافة الأنواع
But if you look in a catalog --
ولكن إذا نظرت في دليل ==
particularly a catalog of modern, beautiful objects for your home --
بالتحديد دليل عن أشياء عصرية وجميلة لبيتك
it looks like this.
سوف تبدو كهذا
There are no cords.
ليس هناك أسلاك
Look next time you get these catalogs in your mail --
إنظروا في المرة القادنمة التي تحصلون بها على هذه الأدلة في بريدكم--
you can usually figure out where they hid the cord.
يمكنكم الاستنتاج أين قاموا بإخفاء الأسلاك
But there's always this illusion that if you buy this lamp,
ولكن يبقى دائماً ذلك الوهم أنك إذا اشتريت هذا المصباح
you will live in a world without cords. (Laughter)
فإنك سوف تعيش في عالم من دون أسلاك
And the same thing is true of, if you buy this laptop
وهذا الشيء ينطبق على شرائك للحاسب المحمول هذا
or you buy this computer -- and even in these wireless eras,
أو هذا الحاسب -- وحتى في هذه العصور اللاسلكية
you don't get to live in the world without cords.
لايمكنك العيش في عالم من دون أسلاك
You have to have mystery and you have to have grace.
عليك أن تكون غامضاً وعليك أن تكون سامياً
And there she is -- Grace.
وها هي == غريس.
This is the most glamorous picture, I think, ever.
أعتقد أن هذه الصورة هي الأكثر روعة على الإطلاق
Part of the thing is that, in "Rear Window,"
وجزء من السبب هو الشباك الخلفي
the question is, is she too glamorous to live in his world?
السؤال هو ، هل هي شديدة الروعة لتعيش في عالمه
And the answer is no, but of course it's really just a movie.
والجواب هو لا، ولكنه بالطبع مجرد فلم
Here's Hedy Lamarr again.
هاهي هيدي لامار مرة ثانية
And, you know, this kind of head covering is extremely glamorous
و،تعلمون هذا النوع من أغطية الرأس هو شديد الروعة
because, like sunglasses, it conceals and reveals at the same time.
لأنه، كما النظارات الشمسية، يحجب ويكشف في نفس الوقت
Translucence is glamorous --
الشفافية مبهرة--
that's why all these people wear pearls.
ولذلك فإن الناس يرتدون الؤلؤ
It's why barware is glamorous. Glamour is translucent --
ولذلك فإن الأواني الزجاجية شديدة الروعة -- الروعة هي الشفافية
not transparent, not opaque.
ليست شفافة وليست غامضة
It invites us into the world
إنها تدعونا إلى العالم
but it doesn't give us a completely clear picture.
لكنها لاتعطينا صورة واضحة كلياً
And I think if Grace Kelly is the most glamorous person,
وأعتقد أنه إذا كانت غريس كيلي الشخص الأكثر روعة
maybe a spiral staircase with glass block may be the most glamorous interior shot,
فإن درجاً حلزونياً مع حوائط زجاجية قد تكون اللقطة الداخلية الأكثر روعة
because a spiral staircase is incredibly glamorous.
لأن الدرج الحلزوني هو شديد الروعة
It has that sense of going up and away,
إنه يمتلك ذلك الحس بالصعود إلى بعيد
and yet you never think about how you would really trip
ومع ذلك لا تفكر مطلقاً بكيفية ترحلك
if you were -- particularly going down.
إذا كنت تحديداً تذهب إلى الأسفل
And of course glass block has that sense of translucence.
وبالطبع فإن الحواجز الزجاجية تعطي هذا الحس بالشفافية
So, this session's supposed to be about pure pleasure
إذاً، هذه الجلسة من المفترض أن تكون ممتعة
but glamour's really partly about meaning.
لكن الروعة حقاً وإلى حد ما هي المعنى
All individuals and all cultures have ideals
كل الأفراد وكل الثقافات لديهم مثال أعلى
that cannot possibly be realized in reality.
لا يمكن نهائياً إدراكه في الواقع
They have contradictions,
لديهم تناقضات
they uphold principles that are incommensurable with each other --
توافقها مع المبادئ غير القابلة للقياس التي تشكل مع بعضها البعض ،
whatever it is -- and yet these ideals give meaning and purpose
مهما تكن، ومع ذلك فإن هذه المثل تعطي معنى وهدف
to our lives as cultures and as individuals.
لحياتنا كثقافات وأفراد
And the way we deal with that is we displace them --
والطريقة التي نتعامل مع ذلك هي أننا نعزلهم--
we put them into a golden world, an imagined world,
نضعهم في عالم ذهبي، عالم خيالي
an age of heroes, the world to come.
عصر من الأبطال، العالم المقبل
And in the life of an individual, we often associate that with some object.
وفي حياة الأفراد، نحن عادة نربط ذلك بمجسم ما.
The white picket fence, the perfect house.
السياج الأبيض، البيت المثالي
The perfect kitchen -- no bills on the counter in the perfect kitchen.
المطبخ المثالي -- لا توجد فواتير في المطبخ المثالي
You know, you buy that Viking range, this is what your kitchen will look like.
تعلمون، أنتم تشترون تلك المجموعة الاسكندنافية، هذا ما سيبدو عليه مطبخكم
The perfect love life -- symbolized by the perfect necklace,
الحب المثالي المجسم في تلك القلادة المثالية
the perfect diamond ring.
الخاتم المثالي ذو الماسة
The perfect getaway in your perfect car.
المهرب المثالي في سيراتك المثالية
This is an interior design firm that is literally called Utopia.
هذه شركة تصميم داخلي تدعى حرفياً أتوبيا ( المدينة الفاضلة )
The perfect office --
المكتب المثالي.
again, no cords, as far as I can tell.
ومرة أخرى، لا أسلاك
And certainly, no, it doesn't look a thing like my office.
وبالتأكيد لا، إنها لا تشبه أبداً مكتبي
I mean, there's no paper on the desk.
أقصد، لا يوجد ورقة على المكتب
We want this golden world.
نحن نريد هذا العالم الذهبي
And some people get rich enough,
وبعض الناس يصبحون أثرياء بما فيه الكفاية
and if they have their ideals -- in a sort of domestic sense,
و إذا حصلو على مثلهم في نوع من الإحساس المنزلي
they get to acquire their perfect world.
فإنهم يحصلون على عالمهم المثالي
Dean Koontz built this fabulous home theater, which is --
العميد كونتز بنى هذا المنزل المسرحي الرائع والذي
I don't think accidentally -- in Art Deco style.
لا أعتقد أنه عن طريق الصدفة -- على نمط فن ديكو
That symbolizes this sense of being safe and at home.
هذا يرمَز هذا الإحساس في كونك آمناً في المنزل
This is not always good, because what is your perfect world?
هذا ليس جيداً دائماً، ما هو عالمكم المثالي؟
What is your ideal, and also, what has been edited out?
ماهو مثالكم، وأيضاً، مالذي تم تعديله؟
Is it something important?
هل هو شيء مهم.؟
"The Matrix" is a movie that is all about glamour.
إذاً، الماتريكس هو فيلم يدور حول الروعة
I could do a whole talk on "The Matrix" and glamour.
يمكنني القيام بمحاضرة كاملة عن الماتريكس و الابهار
It was criticized for glamorizing violence,
لكن تعلمون، أنه تم انتقاده بسبب تصويره العنف بروعة
because, look -- sunglasses and those long coats, and, of course,
لأنه انظروا -- النظارات الشمسية وهذه المعاطف الطويلة وبالطبع
they could walk up walls and do all these kinds of things
يمكنهم المشي على الجدران والقيام بكافة هذه الأشياء
that are impossible in the real world.
المستحيلة في الحياة الطبيعية
This is another Margaret Bourke-White photo.
هذه لوحة بيضاء أخرى لمارغاريت بورك
This is from Soviet Union. Attractive.
هذه من الاتحاد السوفييتي. جذابة.
I mean, look how happy the people are, and good-looking too.
أعني، أنظروا إلى الناس كم هم سعداء، وجميلون أيضاً
You know, we're marching toward Utopia.
تعلمون، نحن نزحف نحو المدينة الفاضلة
I'm not a fan of PETA, but I think this is a great ad.
وتعلمون أني لست معجبة ببيتا، لكن هذا إعلان رائع
Because what they're doing is they're saying,
لأن ما يقومون به هو أنهم يقولون
your coat's not so glamorous, what's been edited out is something important.
معاطفكم ليست شديدة الروعة، ما تم تعديله هو شيء مهم
But actually, what's even more important
ولكن بالحقيقة ما هو أكثر أهمية
than remembering what's been edited out is thinking, are the ideals good?
من تذكر ما تم تعديله هو التفكير، هل المُثُل جيدون.؟
Because glamour can be very totalitarian and deceptive.
لأن الروعة يمكن أن تكون خادعة بشكل شامل
And it's not just a matter of glamorizing cleaning your floor.
وهو ليس موضوع تصوير تنظيف الأرضية على أنه أمر رائع
This is from "Triumph Of The Will" --
هذا من "انتصار الإرادة"
brilliant editing to cut together things.
تحرير رائع لتفريق الأشياء المجتمعة
There's a glamour shot.
هذه لقطة رائعة
National Socialism is all about glamour.
الاشتراكية الوطنية هي عن الابهار
It was a very aesthetic ideology.
لقد كانت فكر جمالي
It was all about cleaning up Germany, and the West, and the world,
كانت عن تنظيف ألمانيا والغرب والعالم
and ridding it of anything unglamorous.
وغربلة كل ما هو غير رائع
So glamour can be dangerous.
لذا فإن الابهار يمكن أن يكون خطيراً
I think glamour has a genuine appeal, has a genuine value.
أعتقد أن الروعة لها نداء حقيقي لها قيمة حقيقية
I'm not against glamour.
أنا لست ضد الروعة
But there's a kind of wonder in the stuff that gets edited away in the cords of life.
لكن هناك نوع من التسائل في الأشياء التي يتم تحريرها في أسلاك الحياة
And there is both a way to avoid the dangers of glamour
وهناك طريقة لتفادي خطورة الابهار
and a way to broaden your appreciation of it.
وطريقة لتوسيع تقديركم لها
And that's to take Isaac Mizrahi's advice
وهنا نأخذ بنصيحة إسحاق ميزراحي
and confront the manipulation of it all,
ومواجهة التلاعب بها كلها
and sort of admit that manipulation is something that we enjoy,
والاعتراف بأن التلاعب هو شيء نستمتع به
but also enjoy how it happens.
ولكن أيضاً نستمتع في كيفية حصوله
And here's Hedy Lamarr.
وها هي هيدي لامار
She's very glamorous but, you know, she invented spread-spectrum technology.
إنها رائعة جداً لكن تعلمون، لقد ابتكرت تقنية انتشار الطيف
So she's even more glamorous if you know that she really wasn't stupid,
إذا، فهي أكثر روعة إذا علمت أنها لم تكن غبية
even though she thought she could look stupid.
حتى ولو أنها اعتقدت أنها من الممكن أن تبدو غبية
David Hockney talks about how the appreciation of this
دايفيد هوكني يتحدث عن كيف أن تقدير
very glamorous painting is heightened if you think about
هذا الرسم الرائع يشتد إذا فكرتم
the fact that it takes two weeks to paint this splash,
في حقيقة أنها اتخذت أسبوعين لرسم هذه اللطخة
which only took a fraction of a second to happen.
والتي تطلبت جزء من الثانية لتحصل
There is a book out in the bookstore --
هناك كتاب في متجر الكتب
it's called "Symphony In Steel,"
يدعى " سيمفونية في المعدن"
and it's about the stuff that's hidden under the skin of the Disney Center.
وهي حول الشيء المخبئ تحت سطح مركز ديزني
And that has a fascination.
والذي يسبب هذه الجاذبية
It's not necessarily glamorous, but unveiling the glamour has an appeal.
ليس بالضرورة أن يكون رائعاً لكن كشف ابهاره هو رائع
There's a wonderful book called "Crowns"
هناك كتاب جميل يدعى "التيجان"
that's all these glamour pictures of black women in their church hats.
عن كل تلك الصور الرائعة لنساء سود تحت قبعاتهن الخاصة بالكنائس
And there's a quote from one of these women, and she talks about,
وهناك اقتباس من أحدى تلك النساء وهي تتكلم عن،
"As a little girl, I'd admire women at church with beautiful hats.
كطفلة صغيرة, كنت لأعجب بالنساء في الكنيسة مع قبعاتهن الجميلة
They looked like beautiful dolls, like they'd just stepped out of a magazine.
يبدون وكأنهم دميات جميلة، وكأنهم خرجو من المجلة للتو
But I also knew how hard they worked all week.
ولكنني علمت أيضاً كم عملوا بجد خلال الأسبوع
Sometimes under those hats there's a lot of joy and a lot of sorrow."
بعض الأحيان يكون تحت تلك القبعات الكثير من السعادة والكثير من الحزن
And, actually, you get more appreciation for glamour
وبالحقيقة فإنك تحصل على مزيد من التقدير للروعة
when you realize what went into creating it.
عندما تدرك ما تطلب الوصل إليها
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.